<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached aboard of the Globe the 18. of May, anno 1617 At an anchor by the Cape of Good Hope, in the Bay of Souldania, 34. degrees to the southward of the æquinoctiall line. By William Lesk, minister of Gods Word. Entertained by the Honourable Companie of Marchants trading into East India, for the instruction and comfort of the fleet, by them sent forth for those easterne parts anno, 1614.</title>
            <author>[Lesk, William].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844150</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8939</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8939)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 842:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached aboard of the Globe the 18. of May, anno 1617 At an anchor by the Cape of Good Hope, in the Bay of Souldania, 34. degrees to the southward of the æquinoctiall line. By William Lesk, minister of Gods Word. Entertained by the Honourable Companie of Marchants trading into East India, for the instruction and comfort of the fleet, by them sent forth for those easterne parts anno, 1614.</title>
                  <author>[Lesk, William].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslowe, and are to be sold at his house neere the east end of Christ-Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached in the Bay of Souldania.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8939:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8939:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED ABOARD of the GLOBE the 18. of <hi>May, Anno</hi> 1617. <hi>At an Anchor by the</hi> Cape <hi>of</hi> Good Hope, in the Bay of SOVLDANIA, 34. <hi>Degrees to the Southward of</hi> the Aequinoctiall line.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM LESK, <hi>Miniſter of Gods Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Entertained by the Honourable Companie of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants trading into Eaſt</hi> India, <hi>for the inſtruction</hi> and comfort of the Fleet, by them ſent forth for thoſe Eaſterne parts <hi>Anno,</hi> 1614. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 71. VERSE, 17, 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O God thou haſt taught mee from my youth: and hitherto haue I declared thy wondrous workes.</p>
               <p>Now alſo, O God, forſake me not, vntill I haue ſhewed thy ſtrength vnto this Generation, and thy power vnto euerie one that is to come.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Purſlowe,</hi> and are to be ſold at his houſe neere the Eaſt end of Chriſt-Church. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8939:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8939:2"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVELY Honorable, and right VVorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Knight, Sir</hi> THO. SMITH, <hi>Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of the Eaſt <hi>India, Muſcouia, Summer Ilands,</hi> and <hi>French Companies, &amp;c.</hi> All increaſe of Grace, Health <hi>and</hi> Happineſſe <hi>in this life, and Glorie in that</hi> which is to come.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>OSEPH</hi> (Honourable Sir) in the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and great goodneſſe of Gods all-ruling prouidence, being by <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> deliuered from the violence and oppreſsion of his mightie, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious enemies, throughout the whole courſe of his life thereafter, testified his thankfulneſſe vnto the great God of Heauen, for ſo comfortable a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, by his effectuall and earnest endeauours,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.33, 34, 35, 36. &amp; 47.11, 12.</note> making both for the aduancement of Gods glorie, and good of the Common-wealth wherein he liued: as his wiſe, graue, and diſcreete counſell for prouiſion against the famine to come, and charitable feeding of the Lords choſen, ſufficiently witneſſe: there needeth no application: for it is a great deale better knowne, then that by my penne
<pb facs="tcp:8939:3"/>the fame thereof can be encreaſed, how ſeriouſly (the ſucceſse ſtill anſwering the zeale and greatneſſe of your endeuours) ſince the firſt time it pleaſed our gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne to caſt his eye vpon your ſingular and rare en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, you haue taken to heart this holy taske. Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing therefore the wiſe and diſcreete carriage of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Embaſſage vnto the Emperour of Muſcouia, by his Maiestie impoſed and laid vpon you, your more then ordinarie care of increaſing the Trade of Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, beneficiall vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l, but eſpecially vnto Ilanders, whereof our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies themſelues being Iudges, wee are inferio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vnto none; your great and manifold aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es vnto farre diſtant and remote Countries, for animating and encouraging of others vnto the like attempts, your bountifull expence and charges vpon new Diſcoueries, your liberall maintaining of men skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the Mathematikes, and other Sciences, making for the direction of Sea-faring men, in conducting their ſhippes into whatſoeuer parts of the world, and, which both in Policie and Pietie exceeds all, your Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration and fauourable acceptance indifferently of all poore diſtreſſed men, in whom ſparkles of Ingenuitie, and ripeneſſe of Iudgement, whereby in time the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth may be benefited, are in any competent meaſure to be ſeene: whence it comes to paſse, that many, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſhould haue lyen buried in the pit of obliuion, for want of preferment, forced to betake themſelues vnto the baſest and moſt ſeruile imployments, liue now in ſome eminencie and places of note in their Countries, being helpefull rather then chargeable vnto others: all which making rather for poſteritie, then preſent gaine,
<pb facs="tcp:8939:3"/>(for what benefit can your gray haires expect by Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Diſcoueries, and other Attempts of that or the like nature?) affoord ſufficient matter of a right large and ample Diſcourſe, being a ſubiect well worthie and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the applauſe and commendation of a learned Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vnto whom (although in dutie as farre obliged as any) leauing the exact performance of ſo great &amp; weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie an employment, I ſhall at this time content my ſelfe with a briefe remembrance of the reaſon mouing me to publiſh theſe ſlender Meditations vnder the couert and ſhade of your protection, I meane your religious care, in furniſhing the Ships and Factories vnder your gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with painefull, learned, and conſcionable Preachers and diſpoſers of the Mysteries of the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, whereby God is glorified in the aſſemblies of your ſeruants, and they themſelues, although (the ſupply of their neceſsities ſo requiring) for a ſeaſon depriued of the benefit and comfort of their Countrey, liue as at home in regard of ſpirituall foode: In which reſpect, as in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, all that loue the proſperitie of Sion, are obliged, and become debtors vnto your deuotion: ſo more particularly, thoſe vnto whom the propagation of Gods worſhip, after a ſpeciall manner, is committed: but of all, moſt eſpecially we, who in this kind haue beene eye-witneſſes of your care, executioners of your zeale, and obiects of your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold and great fauours, for Christ and the Goſpels ſake, conferred and beſtowed vpon vs. The due conſideration whereof, makes me an humble ſuiter, that according to your wonted reſpect, and reuerence of the meaneſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of this nature, you will be pleaſed to ſafegard and protect from the ſlanderous and carping tongues of mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb facs="tcp:8939:4"/>Atheiſts, this ſmall Treatiſe, that vnder your name of all good and godly men iuſtly honoured, comming into the publike view of the world, God in ſome meaſure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by may be glorified, his people edified, and others of your qualitie and condition, as by many other means, ſo by this ſmall exerciſe, vnderſtanding the religious courſe of your gouernment, may thereby be incited and ſtirred vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the like proceedings: according to that of our Sauiour, <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all humble dutie to be commanded, <hi>WILLIAM LESK.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8939:4"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached aboard of the <hi>Globe, riding at Anchor in the Bay</hi> of SOVLDANIA.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 11. Verſe 28.29.30.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Come vnto me all yee that labour, and are heauie laden, and I will giue you rest.</p>
                  <p>Take my yoke vpon you, and learne of me, for I am meeke and lowly in heart: and ye ſhall find reſt vnto your ſoules.</p>
                  <p>For my yoke is eaſie, and my burthen light.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough in the day of his Creation, Man was in the riches of the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and great goodnes of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, made Lord of the World, and Commander of whatſoeuer brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed vpon the face of the Earth;<note place="margin">Gen. 1.18. &amp; 14.</note> the Heauens ſeruing for his vſe, the Earth for his habitation, the Starres for ſignes, for ſeaſons, for dayes and for yeres, and all the creatures as bondmen attending his becke, readie to yeeld homage and obedience vnto him, as their lawfull Commander: yet the Almightie,<note place="margin">Eſay 42.8.</note> who will not giue his glorie vnto another, made him not ſo abſolute, but that ſtill he had a neceſſary dependance and deepely engrauen reference vnto a ſuperior power: for euen in the height and greateſt of his perfection, there was by the finger of God powerfully rooted in the furtheſt and moſt ſecret
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8939:5"/>corners of his heart, a naturall inſtinct, that Honour and Homage was due from him vnto a greater then himſelfe; which directed by an vnderſtanding rightly informed, and affections in nothing ſwaruing from the true verdict and ſound iudgement of the intellectiue part, directly guided, and in all ſafetie conducted this noble creature vnto the great Creator of Heauen and Earth, as the onely true obiect of his ſubmiſſion, vnto whom <hi>Iure creationis</hi> he was in dutie bound to performe obedience. In the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of whom, as he then enioyed all happineſſe; ſo well might he haue ſtill continued in the ſame perfection, if the malice of Sathan had not inclined the freedome of his will vnto the worſer part. But alas, after this dolefull and neuer-ſufficiently lamented alteration, he was in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, by the righteous Iudge of the world, ſo diſarmed and ſtript naked of, if not all, yet the greater part of his former dignitie, that, that which was before the cauſe of his greateſt happineſſe, is now the originall of all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, which in the very rudiments and firſt principles of Religion farre and neere couereth well-nigh the face of the whole earth: for the naturall inſtinct ſpoken off be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſince the fall depriued of the eye of vnderſtanding, whereby it was ſometimes directed in the right way, is now the ground of all the Diuerſitie, Schiſme, and Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which <hi>(proh dolor)</hi> is euery where to be ſeene both in the obiect and manner of diuine worſhip, all men agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon this, that there is a God to be worſhipped, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Heathen,<note place="margin">Cic. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Leg.</note> 
               <hi>Nulla gens tam effera, nulla natio tam barbara, cui non inſideat haec notio, eſſe Deum,</hi> There is (ſayth he) no Nation ſo rude, nor people ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, where this Principle, <hi>That a God is to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,</hi> is not acknowledged and receiued as an vndoubted truth: all (I ſay) agreeing vpon this, but by diſobedience depriued of the eye of righteous iudgement, euer haue, and to this day ſtill doe grieuouſly and groſſely erre, both in finding out the perſon of him that is to be worſhipped,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8939:5"/>and in the manner how, being found, this Homage is to be performed: as eaſily might, at great length, by ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all induction of Nations, Countries, and People, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the Sunne, the Moone, Fire, Water, and other Elements, particularly be dilated, if Hiſtories both ſacred and prophane did not furniſh euery meaneſt capacitie with too too many examples of Catts, Cowes, Stockes, and Blockes, which haue beene thought not vnworthie of diuine worſhip; ſo deepely is this principle, <hi>That there is a God,</hi> rooted in the heart of man, that howſoeuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe beyond all meaſure ambitious and proud, yet rather then he will haue no God, hee can be content to ſubmit himſelfe vnto the baſeſt of the creatures that poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly can be named. Thus man, with <hi>Elymas</hi> the Sorcerer,<note place="margin">Act. 13.11.</note> wandering to and againe, as one deepely plunged in a Labyrinth of more then Aegyptian darkneſſe, ſhould for euer thus haue continued, without ſo much as in the leaſt meaſure approching vnto, much leſſe attaining the end of his labor, if the God of all comfort &amp; conſolation, moued only with pitie &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſeration towards the workmanſhip of his owne hands, had not, beyond all expectation, yea to the great aſtoniſhment both of men and Angels, found out a meanes, whereby man, enforced to ſeeke, but neuer able to find, might be directed vnto the true obiect of that worſhip &amp; obedience, which by a deepely rooted inſtinct he was in duty bound to performe vnto a ſuperior power, in the right acknowledgement &amp; due performance wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of his greateſt felicitie and happineſſe doth conſiſt: which howſoeuer by diuine diſpenſation it was at the firſt reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led onely a farre off,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall tread downe the head of the ſerpent;</hi> and afterwards, for many yeeres to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in that ancient Commonwealth, whereof amongſt all Nations, the Lord was pleaſed to make choiſe for pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his Name from hand to hand, vnder types &amp; figures, darkly conueyed: yet <hi>when the fulneſſe of time was come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>God ſent forth his Sonne, made of a woman, made vnder the Law,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8939:6"/>to redeeme them that are vnder the Law, that we might receiue the adoption of ſonnes,</hi> who from Heauen miraculouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be the Sonne of God, and by the Father anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for the performance of this great and weightie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,<note place="margin">Matth. 3.17.</note> inuites all that deſire the knowledge of the true God,<note place="margin">Eſay 61.1.</note> leauing the by-wayes and beggerly rudiments of worldly elements, to come vnto him as the only meane by the decree and determination of the ſacred Trinitie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for reducing and bringing backe wretched man, ſo farre eſtrayed, vnto the knowledge and vnderſtanding of the true God.<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life: no man commeth vnto the Father but by me: Come therefore vnto me all ye that labour and are heauie laden, and I will giue you reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 11.27.</note> 
               <hi>Come.</hi> Becauſe all things are deliuered vnto me of my Father: So that in me alone is to be found whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is requiſite and neceſſarie for the ſafegard and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your ſoules: for there is none other Name vnder Heauen giuen amongſt men whereby we muſt be ſaued,<note place="margin">Act. 4.12. Ioh. 7.37.</note> but the name IESVS: If any man thirſt, let him come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me and drinke: He that beleeueth in me, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ſaid, out of his bellie ſhall flow riuers of liuing Water: <hi>Come therefore vnto me all ye that labour and are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie laden, and I will giue you reſt.</hi> Secondly, <hi>vnto me.</hi> Come vnto me: Without any the leaſt expectation of Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmes, or immediate reuelations from the Father: For God,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.1.</note> who at ſundrie times, and in diuers manners, ſpake in time paſt to the Fathers, by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt dayes ſpoken vnto vs by his Sonne, whom hee hath appointed heire of all things, by whom alſo hee made the world,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.3.</note> and in whom are laid vp all the treaſures of true Knowledge and Vnderſtanding: Come therefore vnto me, as the ordinarie meanes from aboue appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for effecting and bringing this matter to paſſe. <hi>This is my wel-beloued Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 17.5.</note> 
               <hi>in whom I am well pleaſed, heare him:</hi> For in and by the Mediator betweene God and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8939:6"/>man, God is reconciled vnto man, and man re-vnited vnto his Creator, for the attainement of euerlaſting hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe: <hi>Come therefore vnto me all yee that labour and are heauie laden, and I will giue you reſt.</hi> Thirdly, becauſe the remembrance of former tranſgreſſions, and guilt of ſinne and iniquitie, how manifold or groſſe ſoeuer, ſhould not ſo farre preuaile, as to dishearten or diſcourage vs from vndertaking this holy enterpriſe: Therefore expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſets downe the qualitie and condition of his gheſts, naming euen that which the ſubtiltie and craft of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than might otherwiſe haue haply vſed as a ſtumbling blocke, to hinder and let men from comming vnto him: For how ſoone man begins, in any leaſt meaſure, to thinke vpon reformation of his wicked and euill cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, then our Aduerſarie the Deuill,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> who goeth about as a roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom hee may deuoure, vnmaskes whatſoeuer formerly he hath kept ſecret, and amplifieth to the full thoſe things, which when hee did leaue, he laboured greatly to extenuate and value at the ſmalleſt rate. <hi>Come therefore vnto me all yee that labour and are heauie laden, and I will giue you reſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 61.1.2.3.4.5.</note> becauſe <hi>the Lord hath anointed me to preach good tidings to the meeke, he hath ſent me to binde vp the broken-hearted, to proclaime libertie to the Captiues, and the opening of the Priſon to them that are bound, to proclaime the acceptable yeere of the Lord, and the day of vengeance of our God, to comfort all that mourne in Zion, to giue vnto them Beautie for Aſhes, the Oyle of Ioy for Mourning, the Garment of Praiſe for the spirit of Heauineſſe, that they might be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Trees of Righteouſneſſe, the planting of the Lord, that he might be glorified.</hi> Fourthly, becauſe men, to their endleſſe and irrecouerable loſſe, ſhould not wreſt or peruert that which goeth before in the ſeuen and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth verſe, <hi>No man knoweth the Father but the Sonne, and he to whomſoeuer the Sonne will reueale him:</hi> As if the grace of God were in Chriſt Ieſus offered onely to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8939:7"/>ſome few of thoſe that labour and are heauie laden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burthen of their ſinnes: therefore <hi>(all)</hi> are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. <hi>Come vnto me all yee that labour and are heauie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>and I will giue you reſt.</hi> If your ſinnes were as red as crimſon, come vnto me, and I will make them as white as ſnow: At what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent him of his wickedneſſe, and commeth vnto me, though his ſinnes be as ſcarlet, they ſhall be as wooll: If tenne Lepers come vnto me, although they be euen tenne, they ſhall all be cleanſed of their loathſome and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie diſeaſe: although your ſoules be as blinde with the duſt and durt of Iniquitie, as was <hi>Bartimeus</hi> the begger, come vnto me, and yee ſhall receiue ſight: If your tranſgreſſions be ſuch, and ſo manie, that euen a Legion of Deuills torture and torment your ſoules, come vnto me, and you ſhall finde reſt: If from the Wombe you haue been ſo lame and crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that you are vnable to moue one hayre-breadth towards the Kingdome of Heauen, come vnto mee, and I will enable your ioynts: If you haue ſo long lyen in the puddle of ſinne, that with <hi>Lazarus</hi> you ſtinke in the graue of Iniquitie, come vnto me, and I will breathe in your face the breath of life, whereby you ſhall be made liuing ſoules: where all are inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, there none is excluded: where ſuch as labour and are heauie laden vnder the burthen of Sinne and Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, are willed to come, there a ſecret reaſon is giuen, why the mercie and fauour of God, offered vnto all, is not by all receiued, becauſe all doe not labour, and are heauie laden vnder the burthen of their ſinnes: for Chriſt came not to ſaue the righteous, but to call ſinners to repentance: the whole need no Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, but ſuch as are maymed and lame vnder the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable weight of their tranſgreſſions. Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, for they ſhall be filled.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:8939:7"/>To the end then, that comfortably and with profit wee may come vnto Chriſt, it is neceſſary, that we labour, and be heauy laden vnder the burthen of ſinne, that our hearts be ready to melt, becauſe of our tranſgreſſions, and our ſoules ſtanding at the gates of death, becauſe of the into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable weight of iniquity, which can neuer ſufficiently be effected without a diſtinct knowledge of the nature, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and condition of ſin; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> becauſe the naturall and vnborn <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſelfe loue which deepely lyeth rooted in the heart of man, ſeconded with the malicious ſubtiltie of the common enemy of mans ſaluation, ſo duls and darkens the eye, and edge of his vnderſtanding, that he is more then blind in cenſuring and valuing of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; whence it comes to paſſe, that often he perſwades himſelfe that he is in a direct &amp; ſtraight courſe, or at leaſt meanely to erre, when as he lyes deepely plunged in a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſinke and lothſome puddle of all maner of wickednes: now ſinne is knowne by the Touch-ſtone of Gods Lawe; according to that of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.20. &amp; 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>By the Law is the knowledge of ſinne; I had not knowne ſinne but by the Lawe, for I had not knowne luſt, except the lawe had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not couet;</hi> for whereas all other learning ſerues rather to blowe vp the heart of man with an idle opinion, and vaine conceit of his owne worth, founding nothing els in his eare, but ſhrill and loud blaſts of the excellency of his ſoule, the wonderfull fabricke and making of his body, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſympathie, and fellow feeling, which euery part, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, and power hath one with another, and the ſweet harmonie, and concord of the whole compound, the Lawe of the Lord is that which bewrayeth and layeth open vnto man, the vglineſſe of his heart, the nakednes of his imaginations, and the peruerſeneſſe of his wayes: to the Law therefore and to the teſtimony; if they ſoule ſpenke and thinke not according vnto this word,<note place="margin">Eſay 8.20.</note> it is becauſe there is no light in it; therefore DAVID ſpeaking of this Lawe ſayth, that it is <hi>perfect, conuerting the Soule,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:8939:8"/>that it is <hi>ſure, making wiſe the ſimple,</hi> that it is <hi>right, reioicing the heart,</hi> that it is <hi>pure, enlightening the eyes,</hi> that it is <hi>true, and righteous altogether,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.8, 9, 10. &amp; 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>more to be deſired then gold, yea, then much fine gold, ſweeter alſo then the hony and the hony-combe:</hi> Bleſſed therefore is the man, whoſe delight is in the Lawe of the Lord, and in his Law doth meditate night and day.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe man (naturally) is ſo bewitched with the pleaſures of ſinne, and glued to the alluring, and enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſweetnes of wickedneſſe, that a bare knowledge of the nature of tranſgreſſion, is neuer able to bring this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and weariſomeneſſe vpon his ſoule; therefore, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that by the Lawe wee haue attained vnto the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſinne, it is neceſſary that we vnderſtand the value and eſteeme which it hath in the eyes of the Lord, by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at great length reuealed in his Word; ſometimes, by ſpeeches and words full of diſlike, and diſdaine: <hi>My peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple aske counſell at their ſtockes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>and their ſtaffe declareth vnto them, for the ſpirit of whoredome hath cauſed them to erre, and they haue gone a whoring from vnder their God. God ſaw the wickedneſſe of man that it was great in the earth, and that euery Imagination of the thought of his heart was onely euill continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>therefore it repented the Lord that he had made man vpon the earth, and it grieued him at his heart: your Incenſe and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices are abomination,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe your hands are full of bloud:</hi> ſometimes, he denounceth heauy Iudgements againſt the children of diſobedience, thereby to teſtifie his great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of Iniquity; <hi>The end of all fleſh is come before me, for the earth is filled with violence through them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; behold, I wil deſtroy them with the earth. If thine heart turne away, ſo that thou wilt not heare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 30.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>but ſhalt be drawne away and worſhip other gods, and ſerue them, I denounce vnto you this day, that yee ſhall ſurely pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh:</hi> and ſometimes againe, hee inflicts exemplary pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments vpon ſuch as delight and take pleaſure in the waies therof; as the deſtruction of the primitiue world, the ouerthrow of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and reiection of the Iewiſh Nation ſufficiently witnes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:8939:8"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, becauſe then, commonly, men take moſt to heart offences committed, and feare to belch out miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, wherein otherwiſe they could be content, at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome greedily to wallow, when as they vnderſtand their courſes to bee odious and diſpleaſing vnto men of great power and might: for heerein ſtands the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Princes, and peaſants, that all feare to offend, or giue diſtaſte to the one; whereas no man will reſtraine, or curbe any of the mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt of his deſires, for auoiding the offence of the other; therefore it is requiſite and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to the end that we may labour, and be heauy laden vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burthen of our ſinnes, that we be not ignorant of the vnſpeakeable power, might and maieſty of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God: For this cauſe it was that at the giuing of the Lawe, whereby we come vnto the knowledge of ſinne,<note place="margin">Exod. 19.18.</note> the Lord appeared after ſo fearefull and terrible a manner, that all the people that were in the campe trembled for feare, that thereby ſeeing the greatneſſe of his power, in whoſe ſight ſinne is lothſome and abhorred, they might feare to commit iniquity, and tremble at the remembrance of by gone tranſgreſſions; yea commonly, when as the Almighty publiſheth and proclaimeth vnto the world, his diſlike and deteſtation of ſinne, there are ſtill let fall ſome flaſhes and apparant ſignifications of his might, maieſty, and power: <hi>Thus ſayth the Lord, the Lord of Hoſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 1.24.20.</note> 
               <hi>the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie One of Iſrael, I will eaſe mee of mine aduerſaries, and auenge me of mine enemies. If ye refuſe and rebell, ye ſhall bee deuoured by the ſword: for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, and laſtly, becauſe the nature of man is euer to put from him the euil day, bleſſing himſelfe in his heart, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and ſaying; I ſhall haue peace,<note place="margin">Deut. 29.19.</note> though I walke in the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of my heart, to adde drunkenneſſe to thirſt: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for attaining the effect aforeſayd, it is expedient that men thorowly bee perſwade that the Lord hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a day of recompence, wherein euery man ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded according to that which he hath done in the fleſh,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.6.</note>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:8939:9"/>whether it bee good or bad. Now theſe things thorowly learned,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.5. 2. Cor. 1.14.</note> cannot but bring vs to a true ſenſe and feeling of the heauy burthen and intolerable weight of ſin and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie; and conſequently to labour and be heauie laden vnder the burthen of our tranſgreſſions, wherby we come to haue intereſt in this comfortable inuitation, and are made capable of the large, and ample promiſe annexed thereunto: <hi>Come vnto mee all ye that labour, and are heauy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and I will giue you rest;</hi> not immunity and freedome from the temptations of Sathan, the troubles of the world, and croſſes incident vnto vs whilſt wee liue heere vpon earth: No, no, for through many tribulations we enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdome of heauen; if wee be without chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whereof all are partakers, we are baſtards, and not the Sonnes of God; for the Lord whom he loueth he cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſeth, and he correcteth euery Sonne whom he receiueth: but the words that I ſpeake vnto you are ſpirit and truth; in the world ye ſhall haue tribulation, but in me peace: be of good comfort I haue ouercome the world:<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.33. &amp; 14.27. &amp; 15.11</note> Peace I leaue with you, my Peace I giue you, not as the world giueth giue I vnto you: theſe things haue I ſpoken vnto you that my ioy might remaine in you, and that your ioy might be full. For the reſt which Chriſt here promiſeth vnto ſuch as come vnto him, muſt of neceſſitie be of the ſame nature with his Kingdome, becauſe of temporall felicity he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe publikely profeſſed that <hi>the Foxes had holes, and the Fowles of the heauen had neſts, but the Sonne of man had not whereon to lay his head:</hi> Come therefore vnto me all ye that labour and are heauy laden, and you ſhall haue my ioy fulfilled in you; howſoeuer, as concerning the things of this life,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.13.</note> you muſt reſolue to take vp my yoke, and learne from the intertainment which I haue had in the world, that the Father in this life will not haue his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren free from temptation and trouble: Verely, verily, I ſay vnto you,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.16.</note> the ſeruant is not greater then his Lord, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he that is ſent, greater then he that ſent him: if they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8939:9"/>haue called the Maſter of the houſe <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> how much more ſhall they call them of his houſhold? if they haue perſecuted me, they will alſo perſecute you; take vp there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my yoke and learne of me, for I am meeke and lowly in heart:<note place="margin">Ier. 11.11.</note> I was like a Lambe or an Oxe that is brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſlaughter, and being in the forme of God, made my ſelfe of no reputation, took vpon me the forme of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and was found in faſhion, as a man humbling my ſelfe vnto the death, euen the death of the Croſſe;<note place="margin">Phil. 2 7, 8.</note> learne therfore of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue ſayd theſe things vnto you, ſorrow hath filled your hearts: neuertheleſſe I tell you the truth,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.6, 7.</note> it is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for you to ſtand in the waies, and ſee and ask for the olde pathes and walke therein,<note place="margin">Ier. 6.16.</note> and yee ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules; for though our outward man periſh, yet the inward man is renewed day by day: whoſoeuer then will come vnto me, let him take vp his croſſe and follow mee, for my yoke is eaſie, and my burthen light; becauſe God is faithfull, who will not ſuffer you to be tempted aboue that you are able, but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that ye may be able to beare it;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.16.</note> for the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie by the gracious influence of his holy Spirit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, vpholds, and ſtrengthens his children in the time of trouble, whereby that becomes eaſie and light vnto them, which otherwiſe they could neuer poſſibly bee able to beare, according to that of the Apoſtle: <hi>Bleſſed be God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.1.3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Father of mercies, and the God of all comfort, who comforteth vs in all our tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we may be able to comfort them that are in any trouble, by the comfort wherewith wee our ſelues are comforted of God; for as the ſufferings of Chriſt abounde in vs, ſo our conſolation alſo aboundeth by Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words diuide themſelues into two ſeuerall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in the firſt whereof Chriſt graciouſly inuites all ſuch as labour, and are heauie laden vnder the burthen of their ſinnes, to come vnto him, as the only Phyſicion and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8939:10"/>of perplexed ſpirits, come vnto me all ye that labour and are heauy laden, and I will giue you reſt. The ſecond containes a maine condition, with all care and diligence, ſincerely to be performed by ſuch as accept and embrace this comfortable offer; take vpon you my yoke and learne of me, for I am meeke and lowly in heart, and ye ſhall find reſt vnto your ſoules, for my yoke is eaſie and my burthen light: the inuitation affords theſe particulars to our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; firſt, the exhortation it ſelfe, <hi>Come vnto mee all yee that labour and are heauie laden;</hi> ſecondly, a large and ample promiſe annexed thereunto, <hi>and I will giue you reſt,</hi> or as it is in the next Verſe, <hi>and you ſhall finde rest vnto your ſoules.</hi> In the inuitation we are firſt to conſider the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle or word of exhorting <hi>(Come:)</hi> Secondly, the quality and condition of the ghueſts inuited, <hi>yee that labour and are heauy laden:</hi> Thirdly, the number of them (all:) and Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the feaſt-maker, or he by whom theſe ghueſts are inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>(Me)</hi> come vnto me all ye that labour and are heauy laden: the promiſe after the ſame manner, reſolues it ſelfe into theſe particulars; firſt, the thing promiſed <hi>(reſt)</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the qualitie of it, it is a gift, and thirdly, the guide from whom the ſame is to be expected <hi>(I)</hi> come vnto me, and I will giue you reſt. In the ſecond part of the Text, the condition to be performed by ſuch as accept Chriſts offer is firſt generally propounded, take vpon you my yoke; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the ſame is by two ſeuerall arguments, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enforced, whereof the firſt, ſet downe in the end of the 29. Verſe, is taken from Chriſts owne example; Learne of mee, for I am meeke and lowly in minde: the ſecond, from the facilitie and eaſe of this taske, in that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, for my yoke is eaſie and my burthen light; of theſe then in order, and firſt of the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come:</hi> this word is diuerſly taken in text of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſomtimes it is a word of exhortation, which looking backe vpon ſomething to bee forſaken, implies a ſecret reaſon why departure is to bee made from the ſame, in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8939:10"/>which ſence it is then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly vſed, when as one ſtepping out from the reſt, exhorts &amp; intreats others to enterpriſe or vndertake this or that: thus <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſons vpon the approach of their brother <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> encourage one another, for effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bringing to paſſe their vnlawfull ends;<note place="margin">Gen. 37.20.</note> 
               <hi>Come now therefore and let vs ſlay him, and caſt him into ſome pit, and wee ſhall ſay, Some euil beast hath deuoured him, and we ſhall ſee what ſhall become of his dreames:</hi> and <hi>Balack</hi> in his ſpeech vnto <hi>Balaam, Come, I pray thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 23.27.</note> 
               <hi>and I will bring thee vnto another place, peraduenture it wil pleaſe God that thou maiſt curſe me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from thence:</hi> and in the Parable of the Houſeholder, who going into a farre Countrey, let out his Vine-yard vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tenants, the husbandmen vpon the comming of the Heire, are brought in after this manner, ſpeaking one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, <hi>This is the Heire, come, let vs kil him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 21 38.</note> 
               <hi>and let vs ſeaze on his inheritance. Come</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>and heare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 66.16. &amp; 24.11.</note> 
               <hi>all yee that feare God, and I will declare what the Lord hath done for my ſoule.</hi> And againe, <hi>Come ye children, hearken vnto me, I will teach you the feare of the Lord.</hi> Sometimes againe it is a word of command and charge, as appeareth by the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the two Captaines, whom <hi>Ahaziah</hi> ſent for <hi>Eliah</hi> the Prophet; <hi>Thou man of God, the king hath ſaid, Come downe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kings. 1.9. &amp; 11.</note> 
               <hi>O man of God, thus hath the King ſayd, Come downe quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Both which ſignifications of this firſt word appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the preſent occaſion, afford ſtreames of great comfort and conſolation vnto perplexed ſpirits, that the Sonne of God Ieſus Chriſt ſtepping (as it were) out from amongſt his brethren, ſhould friendly exhort, beſeech and intreat, that forſaking their wretched and miſerable eſtate, the momentarie pleaſures of ſinne, the bondage of Sathan, and allurements of this wicked world; now, at length they would be content to ſhelter &amp; ſafegard themſelues vnder the couert and ſhade of his protection: or otherwiſe for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of his further care, and more earneſt deſire of the ſaluation of our ſoules, that knowing the naturall and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne backwardneſſe of the heart of man, in embracing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8939:11"/>and intertaining motions making for the good and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſſe of his ſoule, he ſhould as Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter commaund, and charge vs leauing our former wicked, and euill courſes, to come vnto him, the onely fountaine and wel-ſpring of true happineſſe: howſoeuer then the words thus expounded afford many ſingular and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie comforts vnto diſtreſſed and diſeaſed ſoules: yet if in this place we vnderſtand (come) to bee the ſame that (beleeue) wee ſhall not come farre ſhort of the true ſenſe and meaning of the ſpeaker; as by collation and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of other Scriptures of like nature euidently doth appeare: <hi>Ye will not come vnto me that ye might haue life; No man commeth vnto the Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.40 &amp; 14.8. &amp; 6.44.</note> 
               <hi>but by mee: No man can come vnto me, except the Father which hath ſent me, draw him:</hi> Faith then in the Mediator Ieſus Chriſt is that, wherby broken and contrite ſpirits, labouring, and heauy laden vnder the burthen of ſinne, finde reſt vnto their ſoules: not a bare knowledge of the Hiſtory of holy Scripture; for then the diuels might challenge intereſt in Chriſts death, as well as others,<note place="margin">Iam 2.19.</note> becauſe Saint <hi>Iames</hi> witneſſeth; The diuels beleeue and tremble: but beſides this knowledge, there muſt bee an aſſurance, grounded vpon the authority of Gods word, that for Chriſt his ſake, God is reconciled vnto vs; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Being not weake in faith, hee conſidered not his owne body now dead, when hee was about an hundred yeere old,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.18, 19, 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>neither the deadneſſe of</hi> Saras <hi>wombe: hee ſtaggered not at the promiſe of God, through vnbeliefe, but was ſtrong in faith, giuing glorie vnto God, beeing fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that what he had promiſed, he was able alſo to performe:</hi> ſo that the ſaith whereby wee come vnto CHRIST, hath his ſeate in both parts of the ſoule, in the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectiue or vnderſtanding part, a ſure and certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth of thoſe things which are to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued; for faith, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth, <hi>is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of things hoped for,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> 
               <hi>and the euidence of things not ſeene.</hi> And againe, <hi>therefore it is of faith, that it might bee by grace,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8939:11"/>to the end the promiſe might be ſure to all the ſeed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>not to that onely which is of the Law, but to that alſo which is of the faith of Abraham, who is the father of vs all.</hi> And in the will, faith leaueth an aſſurance, that God is both able, and in due time wil make good in our particular the generall promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Mercie and Grace, according to that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>I am perſuaded, that neither Death, nor Life, nor Angles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.38, 39.</note> 
               <hi>nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi> Therefore it is, that almoſt euery where the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaking of things, for Chriſt his ſake in due time to be conferred and beſtowed vpon vs, he ſpeaks of them in the time paſt, as if alreadie we were in full poſſeſſion thereof: <hi>Bleſſed be God, the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>who hath bleſſed vs with all ſpirituall bleſſings in heauenly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Chriſt Ieſus, in whom we haue: edemption through his bloud, the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, according to the riches of his grace: but God, who is rich in mercie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.7. &amp; 2.4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>for his great loue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he loued vs, euen when we were dead in ſinnes and treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, hath quickened vs together, and hath made vs ſit together in heauenly places in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Such then is the aſſurance which faith leaues in the heart, that the beleeuer ſpeakes and thinkes of the promiſes of mercie and ſaluation, as of things preſent, whereof alreadie he is in full poſſeſſion: againe, that in faith there is not onely a ſure and certaine knowledge of the Hiſtorie of Gods holy Word, but alſo an aſſurance of the loue and fauour of God in and for the mediation of Ieſus Chriſt, theſe ſubſequent Scriptures ſufficiently witneſſe:<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>Being iuſtified by faith, we haue peace with God, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Now this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that the knowledge of the Hiſtorie of Gods holy Word is ſo farre from quieting and bringing peace vnto the ſoules of men, that on the contrarie, it ſerues rather more and more to encreaſe amazement, feare, and terror in their hearts: according to that of S. <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>The Deuils
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8939:12"/>beleeue, and tremble;</hi> they beleeue, that is, by the Hiſtorie they know the wrath of God to be ſo fierce againſt Sinne and Iniquitie, that it can be expiate and done away by no other meanes, but by the death of his onely begotten Sonne: by the knowledge of the Hiſtorie of Gods holy Word, they vnderſtand themſelues finally, and without all hope of redemption, wholly to be reiected and caſt off: by the Hiſtorie they know, that IESVS is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Iudge both of Men and Angels, and that for euer they ſhall haue their abode in euerlaſting miſerie and torment; therefore they beleeue and tremble. Man likewiſe, in the knowledge of the Hiſtorie, what can hee ſee, but euery where manifeſt tokens of the wrath of God againſt ſinne? as Death, Diſeaſe, and diuers other calamities, vſually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing and befalling vs whileſt we liue here vpon earth; and which moſt of all encreaſeth our feare, that the wrath and indignation of the Almightie is ſuch, and ſo great, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all manner of iniquitie, that it could by no other meanes be appeaſed, but by the death of his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne IESVS CHRIST: all which bringing rather matter of horror and feare, then peace vnto the ſoules of men, there muſt be ſomething elſe beſides Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricall knowledge, in that faith, whereby being iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we haue peace with God; which can be nothing elſe, but an aſſurance of the loue and fauor of Almightie God, in, and for the mediation and all-ſufficient ſacrifice of his dearely beloued Sonne IESVS CHRIST; by whom al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wee haue acceſſe by faith into this grace wherein wee ſtand.<note place="margin">Abak. 1.4.</note> To the ſame purpoſe makes that of <hi>Abbakuk; The iuſt ſhall liue by faith.</hi> No man liueth by an Hiſtoricall knowledge of the Word of God; which, as euen now, at great length, hath been deliuered, furniſheth rather mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of horror, deſperation, and feare, then of life, health, happineſſe, and the like: therefore the faith ſpoken of by the Prophet, muſt, beſides knowledge, be an aſſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to and aſſurance of the loue and fauour of God, in, and for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8939:12"/>the mediation of his Sonne. Thirdly, S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Epheſians, ſo plainely maintaines and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully auoucheth the aſſurance of faith which now we haue in hand, that if there were no more, this one Scripture may well ſerue for confirmation of the ſame:<note place="margin">Eph. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>In whom we haue boldneſſe with confidence by the faith of him:</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Let vs therefore come boldly vnto the Throne of grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>that we may obtaine mercie, and find grace to helpe in time of neede.</hi> Who, knowing onely the Hiſtorie of Gods holy Word, dare preſume boldly and with confidence to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and draw neere vnto the dreadfull Maieſtie of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, whom as an angrie &amp; ſeuere Iudge he ſeeth readie to powre downe the viols of his fierce wrath and indignation vpon the tranſgreſſors of his Law; that faith then, whereby with boldneſſe confidently we preſent our ſelues before God, beſides knowledge of the Hiſtorie, muſt of neceſſitie haue an aſſurance of reconciliation in IESVS CHRIST.<note place="margin">Gen. 4.4.5.24. &amp; 49.20.</note> This is that faith whereby <hi>Abel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came more acceptable in the ſight of the Lord, then his brother <hi>Cain; Enoch</hi> walked with God, and was ſeene no more; <hi>Iacob</hi> dying, tooke order for his buriall in the promiſed Land;<note place="margin">Luke 7.48.</note> and <hi>Marie Magdalene</hi> obtained free pardon and forgiueneſſe of all her tranſgreſſions. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yee haue this faith, Come vnto me all yee that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and are heauie laden, and I will giue you reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Come.</hi> From this, and other Texts of holy Scripture,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> of the ſame or like nature: as, <hi>Call vpon me in the day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>Returne vnto me, and I will returne vnto you: Turne ye now from your euill wayes, and from your euill doings: Waſh yee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>make you cleane, put away the euill of your doings from before mine eyes, ceaſe to doe euill, learne to doe well, ſeeke iudgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 1.16.17.19.</note> 
               <hi>relieue the oppreſſed, iudge the fatherleſſe, plead for the widow: if ye will be obedient, ye ſhall eate the good of the Land.</hi> The <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballats</hi> and ſubtle Sophiſts of theſe laſt dayes gather, I cannot tell what naturall and imborne abilitie and power
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8939:13"/>in man, <hi>ex puris naturaelibus,</hi> as they ſay, to performe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto the Commandements of God; becauſe firſt it were in vaine to exhort, aduiſe, requeſt, and beſeech ſuch as wholly and altogether are impotent and vnable to hearken and obey: againe, the large promiſes of health and happineſſe, in caſe of obedience, were mockages ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then true promiſes, if there were no power at all in man to performe the Commandement; as if ſeeing a man altogether depriued of the vſe of his legges, one ſhould promiſe him great ſummes of money, with all celeritie and ſwiftneſſe, ſpeedily to runne a race, whom hee very well knew vnable ſo much as to ſtand, much leſſe ſwiftly to runne. Being then that the Lord commands, exhorts, aduiſeth, and by large and ample promiſes allures men to the obedience of his Commandements, it muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie follow, that there is ſome power and abilitie in them for the performance of this obedience: Chriſt his Come vnto me, then puts vs in mind, that if wee will, wee may beleeue in the Mediator betweene God and man; if we liſt, there is power in vs ynough to obey his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and if carefully we beſtirre our ſelues, there is no want of ſtrength in our hearts to corporate and worke together with the Spirit of God, for conſummating and bringing to full perfection the worke of our ſaluation; for els the great Shepheard IESVS CHRIST would not require that of vs which altogether we are vnable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme. But needleſſe multiplication and increaſe of words remoued and ſet aſide, if theſe men can be perſwaded to turne vnto the ſixt of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell and foure and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth verſe, they ſhall finde the ſame mouth, that in the Text which now wee haue in hand, inuites and exhorts ſuch as labour and are heauie laden, to come vnto him, there publikely preaching vnto the Iewes: <hi>No man can come vnto me, except the Father which hath ſent me draw him.</hi> Where is now their imborne ſtrength? What is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of their naturall abilitie in ſpirituall things? And
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8939:13"/>of what validitie and force, I pray you, is their ſtrong <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah,</hi> taken from the nature of Chriſts ſpeech? If no man can come, except he be drawne, certainely of our ſelues wee are dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.5.</note> if wee muſt be drawne, then we are not ſufficient of our ſelues to thinke a good thought,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.5.</note> much leſſe to doe any thing that good is: if wee muſt be drawne vnto Chriſt, then naturally e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery imagination of the thoughts of our hearts are onely euill continually. In like manner, the ſame Spirit,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.5.</note> which by the mouth of <hi>Malachie</hi> exhorts Iſrael to turne vnto the Lord their God, by <hi>Ezechiel</hi> profeſſeth,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.7.</note> That he will giue them one heart, and put a new ſpirit within them: That he will take away the ſtonie heart out of their fleſh, and giue them an heart of fleſh,<note place="margin">Ezech. 11.19, 20.</note> that they may walke in his Statutes, and keepe his Ordinances, to doe them, and they ſhall be his people, and he will be their God: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I will giue them one heart, and one way,<note place="margin">Ierem. 32.39.</note> that they may feare me for euer, for the good of them, and of their children after them. That then wee walke in the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Gods commandements, it is the Lords own bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and not any naturall or imborne ſtrength of ours: according to that of S. <hi>Cyprian, Dei eſt, inquam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyp. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Ep. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dei eſt omne quod poſſumus, inde viuimus, inde pollemus, inde ſumpto &amp; concepto vigore hic adhuc poſiti futurorum indicia praenoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus;</hi> Whatſoeuer wee are able to doe for the attaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of euerlaſting happineſſe, is to be aſcribed vnto the grace and gift of God; it is from God, I ſay, and not our owne: for in him wee liue, by him wee are enabled, and from him endowed with ſtrength, liuing yet here vpon earth, by the eyes of faith we behold and looke vpon the badges and notes of euerlaſting happineſſe. And S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> ſpeaking to the ſame purpoſe: <hi>Nemo ſe palpet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Hom. <hi>49.</hi> in Ioan.</note> 
               <hi>de ſuo Satanas eſt: tollat homo peccatum quod ſuum eſt, Deo iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiam relinquat;</hi> Let no man, in the matter of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, aſcribe any thing vnto himſelfe, for of ourſelues we are aduerſaries, and oppoſite vnto the wayes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8939:14"/>Let man then, if hee muſt needes challenge ought to himſelfe, take to him the ſinnefull part, which is his, aſcribing all his righteouſneſſe vnto the Lord. Therefore the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> bluſheth not to begge at the hands of the Lord, euen the beginnings and firſt ſteps of holineſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.10. &amp; 119.18.35.34.35.</note> 
               <hi>Create in me a cleane heart, O Lord, and renew a right ſpirit within me: open thou mine eyes, that I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold wonderous things out of thy Law: make me vnderſtand the path of thy Commandements, ſo ſhall I talke of thy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts: giue me vnderſtanding, and I ſhall keepe thy Law, yea I ſhall obſerue it with my whole heart: make me to goe in the path of thy Commandements, for therein doe I delight.</hi> What then had <hi>Dauid</hi> of his owne? or where was his naturall and imborne ſtrength, whereby he was able of himſelfe to doe ſomewhat towards the attainement of euerlaſting happineſſe? a cleane heart and a right ſpirit he begges to haue created within him: now <hi>creatio eſt ex nihilo,</hi> this is the difference betweene made and created; that making preſuppoſeth the ſubſtance of the thing made, to haue beene before, being nothing elſe in it ſelfe, but <hi>inductio nouae formae,</hi> the bringing of a new ſhape, faſhion, or forme vpon an old ſubiect, as to make a Shippe, a Boat, an Oare, or the like, is nothing elſe but to ſquare and proportion Timber and Wood, which (haply) long, or (at leaſt) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time before hath had his being, into forme and faſhion, fit to ſwimme or ſayle in the Sea: but to create, is of nothing to make ſome ſubſtance. If then <hi>Dauid</hi> muſt haue a cleane heart and a right ſpirit created in him, it will of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie follow, that there was at this time no ſuch thing to be found in his breſt: Secondly, hee cranes not onely a cleane heart and a right ſpirit to be created in him; but <hi>Lord open thou mine eyes, that I may behold wonderous things out of thy Law: giue me vnderſtanding, and I ſhall keepe thy Law: make me to goe in the path of thy Commandements.</hi> As if <hi>Hanna,</hi> hauing by prayer and ſupplication obtained a ſonne at the hands of the Lord, ſhould begge ſafe deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8939:14"/>at the Throne of Gods mercie, profeſſing thereby, both the conception and birth to be from aboue. Iuſt ſo, <hi>Dauid</hi> hauing begged the foundation and ground, a cleane heart and a right ſpirit, finding in himſelfe not ſo much as abilitie and ſtrength, to make vſe of the Lords bleſſings for the ſaluation of his ſoule, much leſſe power to doe any thing that good is, he ſueth, That the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hauing of nothing framed the new man in his heart, he would be pleaſed to open his eyes, that he might ſee, and ſtrengthen his limbes, that hee might walke, and firmely tread within the Courts of his Sanctuarie. Thus then you ſee, what warrant the aduerſarie hath from this and ſuch like Scriptures, for maintaining a poſition ſo preiudiciall vnto the all-ſufficient Sacrifice of Chriſts death. But what then, may ſome man ſay, is the meaning of Gods holy Spirit, in theſe and the like kind of ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? Vnto which queſtion I had rather anſwere by Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> then mine owne mouth: who diſputing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Pelagius</hi> the ſame verie queſtion which now wee haue in hand, ſpeakes after this manner,<note place="margin">Aug. de lib. Arbit. cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iubet Deus quae non poſſumus, vt nouerimus quid ab illo petere debeamus;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ſayth hee) God commaunds vs often to doe thoſe things which he knowes vs wholy vnable to performe, thereby to teach vs what to aske, begge, and craue at his hand. And againe,<note place="margin">Aug. de corrept. &amp; grat. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>O homo in praeceptione cognoſce quid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas habere; in correptione cognoſce tuo te vitio non habere; in oratione cognoſce vnde accipias quod vis habere;</hi> O man, in and by the commandement learne what thou oughteſt to haue; in puniſhment, that thou thy ſelfe art the cauſe of all thy wants; in ſupplication and prayer, vnderſtand from whence ſupply of thy defects is to be had: for as a broken-winged Fowle, by offering to flye, perceiues the defect and decay of that part of her bodie, which before ſhee thought to be ſound; ſo man, being by diuine authoritie commanded to performe theſe and theſe ſpirituall duties, <hi>in ipſo conatu,</hi> in the very attempt and enterpriſe it ſelfe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8939:15"/>he is informed of his owne inabilitie and weakeneſſe. Come then vnto me, doth not, as the Papiſts falſely ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, argue any naturall or imborne ſtrength in man, for the performance of ſpirituall duties, but is a means which it pleaſeth the wiſedome of Almightie God to vſe for bringing of him to the knowledge and acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his naturall and imborne frailtie, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, vnto a begging of things neceſſarie vnto endleſſe and euerlaſting happineſſe, from the Throne of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: according vnto that of S. <hi>Auguſtine, Ideo Iubet vt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere iuſſa conati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 89.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; in noſtra infirmitate ſub lege fatigati, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iutorium gratiae petere nouerimus;</hi> Therefore (ſaith hee) God commands, that in the enterpriſe and attempt of obedience, by reaſon of our manifold infirmities weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnder the yoke of ſo abſolute and perfect a law, wee may learne to ſue vnto the Throne of Gods mercie, for the gracious aſſiſtance of his holy Spirit, whereby we may be enabled to performe that which hee ſo iuſtly doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act and require at our hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto me.</hi> The ſoule of man guiltie of many haynous abominations, and vnderſtanding both the fierceneſſe of Gods wrath and indignation againſt the breach of his Law, and great power which he hath to doe what he will for the ouerthrow &amp; finall ſubuerſion of his enemies, ſeekes nothing more, then how to appeaſe this conſuming fire, and be in fauor with this great and dreadfull Iudge of the World. The Books and Learning of the Heathen are able to afford no direction in this caſe, becauſe they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues blinded with a vaine conceit of Righteouſnes, were altogether ignorant of the great miſerie, by the fall of our firſt parents brought vpon the whole poſteritie. The Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Holy Scripture haue diſcouered two means for ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting and bringing this matter to paſſe, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the Law of Works, &amp; the Law of Faith, <hi>Where is boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting then?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.27.</note> 
               <hi>It is excluded: By what Law? Of Works? Nay, but by the Law of Faith.</hi> The firſt, howſoeuer it be in it ſelfe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8939:15"/>ſufficiently able ſafely to conduct vs vnto the Hauen of euerlaſting happineſſe; yet in regard of our inabilitie and weakeneſſe to performe the condition of perfect obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, contained therein, it becomes rather an accuſer and vpbraider of our miſerie, then a wholeſome ſalue of ſicke and diſeaſed ſoules: according to that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Now we know, that what things ſoeuer the Law ſaith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>it ſaith to them who are vnder the Law, that euery mouth may be ſtopped, and all the world may become guiltie before God: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the deedes of the Law there ſhall no fleſh liuing be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in his ſight, for by the Law is the knowledge of ſinne:</hi> And againe, <hi>The Law worketh wrath, for where no Law is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>there is no tranſgreſſion.</hi> For this cauſe it was, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Preachers of that ancient Church, before the comming of Chriſt, haue from time to time taught Gods people to appeale from this, where no comfort was to be found, vnto the Law of Faith in Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.25.</note> whom God hath ſet to be a propitiation for the remiſſion of ſinnes, through faith in his bloud: that <hi>Adam,</hi> whom the voice of God ſummoning &amp; citing to appeare before the Tribunal of his iuſtice, made afraid, may by a more gentle and milde voice,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.10. &amp; 15</note> 
               <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall tread downe the head of the ſerpent,</hi> be comforted and ſet on foot; and <hi>Dauid,</hi> in whoſe <hi>fleſh there was no ſoundneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.3.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe of the Lords anger, nor reſt in his bones, becauſe of his ſinne,</hi> might in the promiſe of the Goſpel, <hi>In thy ſeed ſhall all the Nations of the world be bleſſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 26.4.</note> fully be ſtrengthened &amp; raiſed vp. Theſe things, in former ages more obſcurely deliuered vnto the faithfull of thoſe times, at Chriſts comming into the world, were publikely and plainely preached vnto the Church: firſt extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily from Heauen, <hi>This is my welbeloued Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth.</note> 
               <hi>in whom I am wel pleaſed, heare him:</hi> and againe, <hi>Feare not, for behold, I bring you good tidings of great ioy which ſhalbe to all people for vnto you is born this day in the city of Dauid, a Sauior, which is Chriſt the Lord: &amp; this ſhalbe a ſign vnto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ye ſhal find the babe wrapped in ſwadling clothes, lying in a manger.</hi> Secondly, a great deale
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8939:16"/>more at large by himſelfe and his Apoſtles: <hi>I am the Dore of the ſheepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.9. &amp; 8.10. &amp; 7.37.38.</note> 
               <hi>by me if any man enter in, hee ſhall be ſaued, and ſhall goe in and out, and finde paſture; I am the light of the world, he that followeth me ſhall not walke in darkeneſſe, but haue the light of life; If any man thirſt, let him come vnto me and drink, he that beleeueth in me, as the Scripture hath ſaid, out of his belly ſhall flow Riuers of liuing water.</hi> The Law iuſtifieth no man without perfect obedience: according to that of <hi>Moſes, Curſed bee hee that confirmeth not all the words of this Law to do them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 27.26.</note> our works euen when they are at the beſt, being fowly bedawb'd with the blots and blemiſhes of the old man, can deſerue nothing but vengeance from him, who in Iuſtice rewardeth, nothing comming ſhort of the leaſt circumſtance and title of his Lawe: Come therefore vnto me, all yee that are weary and heauy laden, and I wil giue you reſt; by faith then in the Sauiour of the world, Ieſus Chriſt, all our ſinnes are forgiuen, and we againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into the fauour of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All</hi> vniuerſality of grace, by vertue of this, and other Scriptures of the ſame or like nature by ſome maintained, and from hence, by others, in large and learned diſcourſes powerfully confuted, I forbeare in this place ſo much as to name, becauſe the words rightly conſidered, giue not the leaſt occaſion of any ſuch diſcourſe, challenging rather the conueiance of comfort vnto the moſt hainous, groſſe, and grieuous ſort of thoſe tranſgreſſours, who labouring, and heauie laden vnder the burthen of their ſinnes, come vnto Chriſt, then any ſuch generall intereſt in Chriſts death vnto all: For as Sathan, the common enemy of mans ſaluation, hath great variety and ſtore of ſleights and ſubtilties to hinder our approach vnto the Throne of grace; ſo this is none of the leaſt, that with great inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and amplifications he ſets before our eyes, the ſins and offences which formerly we haue committed, thereby to make vs deſpaire of Gods goodnes and mercie: this was that Schoole where <hi>Cain</hi> learned that dolefull doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8939:16"/>
               <hi>My ſinnes are greater then can be forgiuen:</hi> this was the ſtratagem which brought wretched <hi>Iudas</hi> vnnaturally to become the executioner of his owne body; to ſpeake nothing of many others, who euen in our times, by this meanes, haue been brought to commit things, farre miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſeeming their holy profeſſion; therefore, for preuenting of ſo great harme, otherwiſe like to enſue and fall vpon the creature, it hath pleaſed the wiſedome of Gods holy Spirit, ſo to publiſh the riches and great depth of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that Sathans ſubtilty may preuaile againſt none, how great and grieuous tranſgreſſors ſoeuer, in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure induſtrious and carefull of the ſaluation of their ſoules: for this cauſe it is, that ſometimes in the plurall number hee is called, the Father of mercies:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed bee God, euen the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Father of mercies, and the God of all comfort, who comforteth vs in all our tribulation, that we may be able to comfort them which are in any trouble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 103.9, 10, 11, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>by the comfort wherewith we our ſelues are comforted of God: ſometimes a mercifull</hi> and gracious Lord, <hi>ſlow to anger, and plenteous in mercie, ſuch a one as will not chide alway, nor keepe his anger for euer, who dealeth not with vs after our ſinnes, nor rewardeth vs after our iniquities; for as high as the heauen is aboue the earth, ſo great is his mercy towards them that feare him: as farre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo farre hath he remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued our tranſgreſſions from vs; like as a Father pittieth his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſo the Lord pittieth them that feare him:</hi> and againe,<note place="margin">Exod. 34.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord, the Lord, mercifull and gracious, long ſuffering, and aboundant in goodnes and truth, keeping mercy for thouſands, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſinne:</hi> and ſometime he is ſaid to be rich in mercy and grace: <hi>God who is rich in mercy, for his great loue wherewith he loued vs, euen when wee were dead in ſinnes, hath quickned vs together with Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>that in the ages to come he might ſhew the exceeding riches of his grace, and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards vs, through Chriſt Ieſus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> and in the Epiſtle to the Romans, <hi>Despiſest thou the riches of his goodnes, forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and long ſuffering, not knowing, that the goodneſſe of God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8939:17"/>leadeth thee to repentance: I will ſpare them</hi> (ſaith the Lord, by the mouth of the Prophet) <hi>as a man ſpareth his own ſonne that ſerueth him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note> There is then no ſin ſo odious and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in the ſight of God, but vpon a true ſenſe and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the lothſomneſſe of the ſame, by faith, in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, Ieſus Chriſt, free pardon and forgiueneſſe is aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly to be looked for, and expected from the Throne of mercie, and grace: Come therefore vnto me all ye that are weary and heauy laden, and I will giue you reſt: <hi>though your ſinnes be as skarlet, they ſhall be as white as ſnow, though they bee redde as crimſon, they ſhall be as wooll; for if the wicked will, turne from all his ſinnes that he hath committed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 18.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>and keepe all my ſtatutes, and doe that which is lawfull and right, he ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liue, he ſhall not dye; all his tranſgreſſions that hee hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, they ſhall not be mentioned vnto him, in his righteouſneſſe that he hath done he ſhall liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye that labour,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch as be skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the original tongues, make this difference between <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that the latter generally ſignifying whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer labour, exerciſe and trauaile; the firſt betokeneth a paineful, weariſome, ſorrowfull, and heauy labour, ſo that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, labour is the cauſe of weariſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or painefull, and tedious emploiment; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Septuagint, and other Tranſlations of the olde Scripture into the Greeke tongue, haue vſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in ſuch places of the old Teſtament where the Originall expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſuch and ſo great ouerſpending of the vitall parts, by reaſon of too much ſorrow, griefe, labour and toile, that without preſent ſuccour, releefe, and comfort, nothing but death and fearefull diſſolution is vndoubtedly to bee expected: as in that of <hi>Deuteronomy, Remember what</hi> Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lek <hi>did vnto thee by the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 25.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>when ye were come forth out of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, how hee met thee by the way, and ſmote the hindmoſt of thee, euen all that were feeble, behind thee, when thou waſt faint and wearie.</hi> And againe, <hi>Ahitophel</hi> offering his ſeruice vnto <hi>Abſalon</hi> againſt <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 17.2.</note> ſayth, <hi>I will come vpon him while he is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8939:17"/>weary and weake handed, and will make him afraid: I haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you a Land, for which ye did not labour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.13.</note> 
               <hi>and Cities which yee built not, and ye dwell in them: What!</hi> Did not <hi>Iſrael</hi> labour for the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> for which they had many ſharpe skirmiſhes, and encountred with many ſeuerall oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Yes verily, but becauſe of the extraordinary aſſiſtance of Gods holy Spirit, and vnaccuſtomed preſence of his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power, and out-ſtretched arme, whereby they ſubdued thoſe nations with great facility and eaſe, they might well haue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but they had not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it was vnto them ſome kinde of exerciſe, but not an ouer-ſpending, and out-wearing of their ſtrength; ſometimes againe, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is vſed, for expreſſing of thoſe places of the old Teſtament, where the Originall ſignifieth a coniunction of labour, ſorrow, trauell, heauineſſe and paine: <hi>Man is borne vnto trouble, as the ſparks flye vpwards.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 5.7.</note> And againe, <hi>the daies of our yeeres are threeſcore and ten, and if by reaſon of ſtrength they be foureſcore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.10.</note> 
               <hi>yet is their ſtrength labor and ſorrow.</hi> Thirdly, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is vſed by the Pen-men of holy Scripture, for expreſſing the varietie of tribulation, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and croſſe, vnder which in this life the Saints conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually groane:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Euen vnto this preſent houre we both hunger and thirſt, and are naked, and are buffeted, and haue no certaine dwelling place,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and labor working with our owne hands.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.10.</note> And againe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>for therefore wee labour and ſuffer reproach, becauſe we truſt in the liuing God who is the Sauiour of all men, eſpecially of thoſe that beleeue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.9.</note> and in the 26. of S. <hi>Mathews</hi> Goſpell, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Why trouble ye the woman, for ſhee hath wrought a good worke on mee?</hi> In like manner, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in wearineſſe and painfulneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.27.</note> 
               <hi>in watchings of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, in hunger and thirſt, in faſtings often, in coldneſſe and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> and againe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>neither did wee eate any mans bread for nought,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>but wrought with labour and trauell, night and day, that wee might not be chargeable vnto any.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:8939:18"/>From hence then it is eaſie to vnderſtand who, and what manner of ghueſts they be, whom Chriſt ſo friendly exhorts, all by-reſpects ſet aſide, directly to come vnto him: Firſt, ſuch as either in the Ceremonies of the ancient Law, the traditions of men, or preciſe and ſtrict perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Morall Law, with great labor, perplexitie, &amp; trouble, ſeek the fauor of God, peace of conſcience, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting happines; but after vnexpreſſible anguiſh, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding rather further torture &amp; torment of conſcience, then any leaſt beginnings of eaſe, are ready to giue ouer, as men by their owne endeuours wholly and altogether vnable to ſtand in the preſence of a conſuming fire; thoſe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt louingly inuites, not to deſpaire in this their wreſtling with the wrath of God, nor any longer to confide and truſt in their owne righteouſneſſe, whence no comfort at all is to be expected; but altering their courſe, to come, or beleeue in him, vnto whom all things requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite and neceſſary for the ſafegard, and ſaluation of mens ſoules are giuen of the Father, vnto which ſenſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or heauy laden, fitly doth agree: for the Law is by the Prophet,<note place="margin">Eſay 9.4.</note> compared to a burthen, <hi>Thou haſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the yoke of his burthen, and the ſtaffe of his ſhoulder, the rodde of his oppreſſour, as in the day of</hi> Midian: and againe, They binde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, heauy burthens and grieuous to bee borne, and lay them on mens ſhoulders, but they themſelues will not moue them with one of their fingers;<note place="margin">Mat. 23.4.</note> ſuch then as confident in their owne ſtrength, haue ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly endeuoured the atonement of Righteouſneſſe, by the workes of the Lawe, but by experience, finding the heauineſſe of this yoke, and greatneſſe of their inability, by their owne endeuours, to ſtand in the preſence of ſo great and terrible a Iudge, are truly humbled and caſt downe, vpon the ſenſe and feeling of this their weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſuch (I ſay) are fit ghueſts for CHRISTS Table, as appeareth by his reply vpon the Phariſes modeſt and diſcreete ſpeech,<note place="margin">Marke 12.34</note> 
               <hi>Thou art not farre from the Kingdome of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8939:18"/>Heauen.</hi> The ſecond ſort of ghueſts, whom by theſe words Chriſt ſo fauourably inuites to come vnto him, are thoſe, who vpon a ſenſe and feeling of their manifold tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, the apprehenſion of the wrath of God, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the laſt day, are at the pit and pinch of deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelfe, wherunto alſo the word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, very fitly doth accord and agree; for <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaking of the burthen of ſin and wrath of God, ſayth, <hi>He hath borne our griefes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 3.4.11.</note> 
               <hi>and carried our ſorrowes, yet did wee eſteeme him ſtricken, ſmitten of God and afflicted: he ſhall ſee the trauell of his ſoule and ſhall be ſatisfied, by his knowledge ſhall my righteous Seruant iuſtifie many, for hee ſhall beare their iniquities:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 5.7.</note> and <hi>Zacharie</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to this ſame purpoſe ſayth, that <hi>Wickednes ſitteth vpon a talent of lead:</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh of tranſgreſſion, as of a heauy burthen: <hi>Mine Iniquities are gone ouer mine head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.4.</note> 
               <hi>as an heauy burthen they are to heauie for me;</hi> ſo that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without either violence or ſtrayning, are properly vnderſtood of ſuch as labour and are heauy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, vnder the weight and intolerable burthen of their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſuch as vnder the heauie burthen of croſſe and calamitie are grieuouſly perplexed, and borne downe, but finding no eaſe, nor way to eſcape, are ready well-nigh to ſinke vnder the burthen; thoſe, Chriſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly and friendly exhorts, not becauſe of their preſent calamities to thinke themſelues caſt off of God, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred from the Kingdome of Heauen; but all ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes ſet aſide, to come vnto him where vndoubtedly they ſhall finde reſt vnto their ſoules, either by a finall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouall of their calamitie, as <hi>Hanna, Mordecai, Rebecca,</hi> and diuers others: or mitigation, and aſſwaging the heat of their tribulation,<note place="margin">Gen. 39.21. Dan. 6.12. &amp; 3.23.</note> as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> whilſt hee liued in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Iayle, <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lyons denne: or if their further good require continuance in tribulation, by the ſweete influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his holy Spirit, quieting and calming their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed and perplexed ſpirits in the agonie and greateſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8939:19"/>heate of the fierceſt temptations, as <hi>Stephen</hi> in his martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>Dauid</hi> in the dayes of his ttouble, and the bleſſed Apoſtles in their ſeueral perſecutions for the Goſpels ſake. Theſe then being the ghueſts, whom ſo louingly Chriſt bids, and comfortably inuites to come vnto him; it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie from bence to vnderſtand who they be that debar and make themſelues vncapable of the grace of Chriſt: Firſt, ſuch as drunke with a vaine conceit and opinion of their owne righteouſneſſe, thinke themſelues ſufficiently able to performe and obey the commandements of the Lord, and conſequently feele not themſelues labouring, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie laden vnder the burthen of their ſinnes: Secondly, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures, and all ſuch as weigh not, nor regard their ſinnes, thinke not vpon the wrarh of God, and terror of the laſt Iudgement, but careleſly contemne, neglect and deſpiſe the ſame; of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaking, ſayth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>who being paſt feeling, haue giuen themſelues ouer vnto laſciuionſneſſe, to worke all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe with greedineſſe:</hi> Thirdly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch as beſotted with the dainties and ſoft allurements of the world, feele not their miſerable and wretched eſtate, in regard of their manifold tranſgreſſions and dreadfull Iudgement of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, nor think vpon the fauour and grace of God here, and euerlaſting happineſſe in the life to come: Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and laſtly, ſuch as vpon the ſenſe and feeling of their ſinnes, and apprehenſion of Gods wrath and indignation againſt them for their tranſgreſſions, beeing thorowly humbled and caſt downe, chooſe rather to ſink in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit of death and deſperation, then to come vnto Chriſt Ieſus, the Spirituall Phyſicion, and Comforter of ſicke and diſeaſed ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I will giue you reſt.</hi> Feare of puniſhment, and hope of reward, are two maine motiues, whereby man is either encouraged in the wayes of godlineſſe. or reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from tranſgreſſing the Commandements of the Lord: and therefore in the booke of the Law, where
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8939:19"/>ſummarily, and in generall, is ſet downe whatſoeuer elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where throughout the Text of holy Scripture is more at length deliuered, <hi>Moſes</hi> vnder thoſe two comprehends all the motiues which poſſibly can be deuiſed and found out, eyther for animating and encouraging of man vnto the better things, or diſſwading of him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worſt, <hi>See, I haue ſet before thee this day life and good, death and euill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 30.15, 16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>in that I command thee this day to loue the Lord thy God, to walke in his wayes, and to keepe his commandements, and his ſtatutes, and his iudgements, that thou mayeſt liue and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie, and the Lord thy God ſhall bleſſe thee in the Land whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou goeſt to poſſeſſe it: but if thine heart turne away, ſo that thou wilt not heare, but ſhalt be drawne away, and worſhip other gods, and ſerue them, I denounce vnto you this day, that yee ſhall ſurely periſh, and that yee ſhall not prolong your dayes vpon the Land whither thou paſſeſt ouer Iordan, to goe to poſſeſſe it.</hi> And againe, <hi>It ſhall come to paſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 38.1.15.</note> 
               <hi>if thou ſhalt hearken diligently vnto the voice of the Lord thy God, to obſerue and doe all his commandements which I command thee this day, that the Lord thy God will ſet thee on high, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all Nations of the earth: but if thou wilt not hearken vnto the voice of the Lord thy God, to obſerue and doe all his commandements and his ſtatutes which I command thee this day, that all theſe curſes ſhall come vpon thee, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take thee.</hi> In like manner haue the Lords proceedings beene with particular perſons:<note place="margin">Gen. 4.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>And the Lord ſaid vnto</hi> Cain, <hi>Why art thou wroth, and why is thy countenance fallen? if thou doe well, ſhalt thou not be accepted? and if thou doeſt not well, ſinne lyeth at the dore.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſet vp thy Seede after thee, which ſhall proceed out of thy bowels, and I will eſtabliſh his kingdome; I will be his father, and he ſhal be my ſonne: if he commit Iniquity, I will chaſten him with the rodde of men, and with the ſtripes of the children of men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kings 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>If thou wilt walke in my wayes, to keepe my ſtatutes and commandements as thy Father</hi> Dauid <hi>did walke, then I will lengthen thy dayes.</hi> And here, in the Text which now we haue in hand, Chriſt friendly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiting
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8939:20"/>ſuch as labour and are heauie laden, to come vnto him, the exhortation is enforced by an ample and large promiſe of reward, <hi>Come vnto me all ye that labour and are heauie laden, and I will giue you reſt.</hi> For as the elements of the world naturally incline each of them to his owne Region and place of abode: ſo the ſoule of man, by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion hauing fallen from his reſt, is ſo perplexed and wearied, wandering to and againe, that it hearkens vnto nothing more willingly, then motions and means ſeruing for that purpoſe:<note place="margin">Confeſſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> according to that of S. <hi>Auguſtine, Cor noſtrum creaſti ad te Domine, &amp; niſi te, nunquam ſatiari po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt;</hi> O Lord, thou haſt created our ſoules to thine owne image, ſo that but in thee they neuer receiue content. Which our Sauior well conſidering, vſeth the ſame as an vnfaileable argument to induce and perſwade vs to come and drinke freely of the waters of life, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and I will giue you reſt. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſed, when as after labour and toyle we betake our ſelues vnto tranquillitie and eaſe, for refreſhing of our wearie, ouer-ſpent, and decaying ſtrength: as in that of <hi>Lucian,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, after long and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſickneſſe receiuing or enioying reſt: and <hi>Suidas,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who would not out of miſerie and tedious employment, come vnto reſt? And thus the Greeke Tranſlation vſeth the word, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the Lords ſpeech vnto <hi>Dauid,</hi> concerning his ſonne <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Chron. 22.9.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, a ſonne ſhall be borne vnto thee, who ſhall be a man of reſt, and I will giue him reſt from all his enemies round about him.</hi> But moſt frequently in the text of holy Scripture, this word is vſed to expreſſe the tranquillitie and calmeneſſe of the mind: as in the fift of Geneſis, and nine and twentieth verſe, old <hi>Lamech</hi> ſuppoſing that his ſonne had beene the Meſſias promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Garden, calls him <hi>Noah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>This ſonne ſhall comfort vs, concerning our worke and toile of our hands, becauſe of the ground which the Lord hath curſed.</hi> Where
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8939:20"/>the Greeke Tranſlations vſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto our Sauiour alluding, ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Come vnto me, and I will giue you reſt. Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs thereby to vnderſtand, that he is that true <hi>Noah,</hi> from whom the holy Patriarchs, labouring vnder the burthen of ſinne and iniquitie, did expect and looke for reſt vnto their ſoules. In like manner, the day of feſtiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ioy, which the Iewes celebrated vpon the newes of their deliuerance from the trecheries of wicked <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and ſentence of death formerly paſſed vpon them, is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a day of reſt and tranquillitie. And againe, the refreſhment which <hi>Saul,</hi> vexed with the euill ſpirit, receiued by <hi>Dauids</hi> Muſike, the Greeke Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation expreſſeth it by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.23.</note> ſo <hi>Saul</hi> was refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and was well, and the euill ſpirit departed from him. From hence then it is eaſie to vnderſtand the nature of this promiſe, which Chriſt here in the Text makes vnto ſuch, as labouring and heauie laden vnder the burthen of their ſinnes, come vnto him for reliefe and comfort, <hi>viz.</hi> in this life, refreſhment, reſt, and eaſe vnto their ſoules, from the conſuming heat of Gods wrath, the rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe of ſinne, and heat of the torment, and torture of conſcience, which formerly they haue endured; and in that which is to come, perfect ioy, felicitie, and happines, being freed from all miſerie whatſoeuer. Therefore S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> calls the time of Chriſts comming vnto iudgement, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the times of refreſhing, or reſt. What paines are anſwerable vnto ſo great a reward? Shall not the children of this life riſe vp and condemne vs in the laſt day, who refuſe no trauell, perplexitie, and trouble, for attainement of worldly preferment? Which gotten, is firſt corruptible, and ſubiect to the out-wearing power of time; ſecondly, vncertaine, and doubtfull, after a world of miſerie and trouble vndertaken for attainement of the ſame. I will not now ſpeake of <hi>Alexander</hi> his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes, in ſubduing Aſia, of <hi>Annibal</hi> his labours, in paſſing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8939:21"/>from Spaine ouer the Alpes into Italie, <hi>Xerxes</hi> his perple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xitie during his abode in Europe, together with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that nature: whereof ſome, after vnſpeakable paines, haue come ſhort of their ends, as <hi>Xerxes</hi> of the conqueſt of Europe, <hi>Annibal</hi> of Italie, <hi>Craſſus</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> of Perſia: others, after great labor and paine, haue ſtill continued vncertaine, fearefull, and in doubt, till the very moment and laſt period of enioying their ends. What warrant had <hi>Alexander</hi> for his aſſurance of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing Aſia? <hi>Auguſtus</hi> of <hi>Pompey, Caſſius</hi> and the like? and all ſubiect to corruption; for where are now the great Monarchies of <hi>Aſſyria, Media, Perſia, Grecia,</hi> and of the <hi>Romans?</hi> well then, being that men vndergoe ſuch and ſo great labour and toyle, for attaining vncertaine and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible glorie, what ſhould we do for attaining the reſt ſpoken of here in the Text, which once gotten, is free from all corruption, and whereof by the means here mentioned, we may vndoubtedly be aſſured?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take vpon you my yoke.</hi> As man by nothing more is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to vndertake great &amp; weighty matters, then by hope and expectation of reward, ſo failing and comming ſhort of his ends, he ſeldome miſſeth ſhamefull Apoſtaſie, and defection from his former reſolution; yea oftentimes, although the error be in his owne falſe conceit, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding of the promiſe. Thus Iſrael hearing in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, that a Land flowing with milke and hony was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them, and that the Lord himſelfe would ſafely conduct them into that good Land; O they are a fire, till the iourney be in force; but how ſoone as come to the red Sea, they ſee themſelues enuironed with great and high mountaines on the one ſide, the Aegyptian forces on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the raging waues of mercileſſe water before their faces, how ſoon they came into the deſart and barren wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and heard of the great ſtrength and walled Cities of Canaan, as men fruſtrate and diſappointed of their promiſed reward, like broken bowes they ſtart backe, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8939:21"/>make defection from their former profeſſion. Many, in hope and expectation of future preferment, followed Chriſt in the beginning of his Miniſterie, fondly drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of a temporall kingdome: but perceiuing, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of time, all things to fall out quite contrarie, the Text ſaith, <hi>That they went backe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.66. 2. Tim. 4.10. Luk. 22.4.</note> 
               <hi>and walked no more with him.</hi> This was <hi>Demas</hi> his bane, <hi>Iudas</hi> his ruine, <hi>Simons</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow, and a great ſtumbling blocke vnto the two diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples iournying towards Emmaus, as by their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference euidently doth appeare,<note place="margin">Act. 8.19.</note> 
               <hi>We truſted that it had beene he which ſhould haue redeemed Iſrael: beſide all this, to day is the third day ſince theſe things were done: yea, and certaine women alſo of our companie made vs aſtoniſhed, which were early at the Sepulchre, and when they found not his bodie, they came, ſaying, that they had alſo ſeene a viſion of Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24.21, 22, 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>which ſaid, that he was aliue.</hi> Therefore Chriſt, for preuenting of this ſo great an inconuenience, hath from time to time laboured rightly to informe ſuch as come vnto him, of the nature and qualitie of the entertainment, which from his hands is to be expected. Thus the Phariſee offering his ſeruice, heareth, That <hi>the Foxes haue holes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>and the Birds of the Heauen haue neſts, but the Sonne of man hath not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to lay his head.</hi> And here, in the Text which now wee haue in hand, hauing comfortably inuited all ſuch as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and are heauie laden vnder the burthen of their ſins, to come vnto him, with a promiſe of reſt; leſt men here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhould promiſe vnto themſelues worldly pleaſure, temporall felicitie, and the fulfilling of the delights and deſires of the fleſh, the miſſing whereof might afterwards occaſion a diſgracefull apoſtafie and defection from this holy profeſſion: therefore after the promiſe, immediately he ſubioynes a large commentarie and expoſition of his former words, <hi>Take vpon you my yoke:</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaid, I came not to cleanſe you from your ſinnes, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reconciled and receiued againe into the loue and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of Almightie God, you ſhould challenge libertie and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8939:22"/>freedome, without all reſtraint, at randon to wallow in ſinne and iniquitie: it is neither a bodily nor fleſhly reſt, which from me is to be looked for and expected; for why ſhould the followers of a Prince, whoſe kingdome is not in this world, dreame of ſuch things? but the reſt which I promiſe, is ſpirituall, Come vnto me, and you ſhall find reſt vnto your ſoules. As concerning the things of this life, you muſt learne to put off, concerning the former conuerſation, the old man, which is corrupt, according to the deceitfull luſts, and be renewed in the ſpirit of your mind, putting on the new man, which after God is crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe. Our freedome in Chriſt Ieſus then is not ſuch, that as lawleſſe men we may doe what we liſt: but on the contrarie, being ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into his myſticall bodie, wee muſt take vpon vs his yoke of repentance and faith; by the one putting off, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our former conuerſation, the old man, which is corrupt, according to the deceitfull luſts; and by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being renewed in the ſpirit of our minds, putting on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and true holineſſe. Neyther is the Reſt by Chriſt Ieſus promiſed, a ceſſation of tribulation and croſſe, but by faith being vnited vnto the great Shepheard, we muſt take vpon vs his yoke of calamitie and trouble: If any man will come after me, let him deny himſelfe, and take vp his croſſe,<note place="margin">Matth. 16.24.</note> and follow me. <hi>Take vpon you my yoke:</hi> The word yoke, in his proper ſignification, is an inſtrument framed by the wit and inuention of man, for combining and ioyning beaſts together in Carts or Coaches, for the more eaſie and ſwift carriage of ponderous and weightie things; wherein three things offer themſelues to our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration: firſt, a diſtinct and ſeuerall kind of labor and working; for beaſts vnder the yoke are confined vnto one particular manner of trauaile: ſecondly, the weight and heauineſſe of the burthen; for yoking preſuppoſeth an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in the owner, to lay more vpon the beaſts then
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8939:22"/>otherwiſe conueniently they could be brought to beare: and thirdly, the crueltie of the Dryuer; becauſe beaſts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yoke, reſtrained from working as they would, are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly puſht and prickt forward with goades, whips, ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the like: From which three properties of a yoke, the Pen-men of holy Scripture haue drawne three ſeuerall metaphors, vſing the word ſometimes for the doctrine, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and teaching, wherein the Lord traines and brings vp his Church here vpon earth: becauſe as a yoke confines beaſts vnto a definite and certaine kind of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; ſo doctrine, inſtitution, and teaching, commaunds vs to thinke, ſpeake, and doe after this or that manner: <hi>Theſe haue altogether broken the yoke, and burſt the bonds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5.5.</note> that is, they haue forſaken and caſt off the obedience of Gods commandements. If in this ſence we vnderſtand Chriſt his words, the meaning will be, that by faith in his death we are not ſo freed from the yoke of his Law, as that we haue libertie to doe what wee liſt; but by faith in the Mediator being reconciled vnto God, we are to take this yoke vpon vs, vſing the Law as a guide, a path, and ſure way, to walke and paſſe through the wilderneſſe of this life, into the ſpirituall Canaan of euerlaſting happineſſe. Herein then ſtands the difference betweene Chriſtians and Iewes, as concerning the workes and obſeruation of the Morall Law, that the one is bound to a ſtrict performance of the exquiſite and exact iuſtice required therein, vpon paine of death and euerlaſting damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: according to that of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 27.26.</note> 
               <hi>Curſed be he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth not all the words of this Law, to doe them.</hi> But Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the curſe of the Law;<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> ſo that wee are not confined within theſe ſtraits, eyther by perfect and abſolute obedience to purchaſe life, or in caſe of defect and failing in the leaſt, to expect the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſentence of death and damnation to paſſe vpon vs; howſoeuer a ſerious and earneſt endeuour be required in putting off, concerning our former conuerſation, the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8939:23"/>old man, which is corrupt according to the deceitfull luſts,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.20.</note> and putting on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe, being not without law to God, but vnder the law to Chriſt: for the more that wee are bound to the mercie and fauour of God, the more are wee obliged to conforme our ſelues to his good will and pleaſure.<note place="margin">Rom. 9.21.</note> Being then, that by faith in his Sonne we are freed from the curſe of the Law, the Father, for Chriſt his ſake, accepting our halfe-mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and imperfect obedience as abſolute and without blame, let it beget in our hearts rather a more earneſt endeuour of performing the Law, as a perfect path of righteouſneſſe, then careleſſe Epicuriſme, in following our owne wayes; profeſſing and ſaying with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.22.</note> 
               <hi>I delight in the Law of God, after the inward man.</hi> Sometimes againe, becauſe of the ſecond proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the word <hi>Yoke</hi> is vſed for the heauie burthen, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie, and ſorrow, which in caſe of diſobedience the Law bringeth vpon the ſoules and conſciences of men, in which reſpect the Law is often called a yoke:<note place="margin">Act. 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>Why tempt yee God, to put a yoke vpon the necke of the Diſciples, which neither our fathers nor wee were able to beare?</hi> that is, Why labour yee to intangle and bring againe within the curſe of Gods Law thoſe, who by faith in Chriſt may well be freed there-from?<note place="margin">Gal. 5.1.</note> And againe, Stand faſt in the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wherewith Chriſt hath made vs free, and be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled againe with the yoke of bondage: in which ſenſe, Chriſt his <hi>my yoke</hi> imports an Antitheſis and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition betweene the Law of Faith and the Law of Workes: as if he ſhould haue ſaid, You haue heretofore laboured and beene heauie laden vnder the intolerable yoke and heauie burthen of the Law, which was neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to afford you any comfort, or giue reſt vnto perplexed ſpirits;<note place="margin">Rom. 3.20.</note> for by the deeds of the Law there ſhall no fleſh li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing be iuſtified in his ſight: take therefore vpon you my yoke of the Goſpel, &amp; you ſhall find reſt vnto your ſoules.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8939:23"/>Sometimes, becauſe of the third propertie, the word yoke is vſed, for the hard vſage, calamity and tribulation, which men receiue &amp; indure at the hands of others; <hi>Of old time I haue broken thy yoke, &amp; burst thy bonds:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 2.20. &amp; 28.2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Thus ſpeaketh the Lord of Hoſts, the God of Iſrael, ſaying, I haue broken the yoke of the King of Babylon:</hi> and againe, <hi>I haue put a yoke of Iron vpon the necke of all theſe Nations, that they may ſerue</hi> Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar <hi>King of Babylon.</hi> And in this ſenſe (although I neither dare, nor doe reiect the former) after a ſpeciall manner are Chriſt his words here to be vnderſtood, that in this life ſuch as come vnto him, ſtand in neede of calamity and tribulation, for ſuppreſſing and keeping downe the exorbitant wickedneſſe, and vnruly wantonneſſe of the fleſh. Take vpon you my yoke, then is the ſame with that of our Sauiour: If any man will come after mee,<note place="margin">Mat. 16.24. &amp; 10.30.</note> let him deny himſelfe, and take vp his croſſe and follow me: and againe, He that taketh not his croſſe and followeth mee, is not worthy of me: Whoſoeuer will come after me, let him deny himſelfe, and take vp his croſſe and follow me.</p>
            <p>The happineſſe then which wee finde in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Marke 8.34.</note> doth not conſiſt in the delights and pleaſures of the fleſh, but in the quieting calmeneſſe of the mind: Come vnto me and ye ſhall find reſt vnto your ſoules; let vs not then bee diſmaied or caſt downe, if ſo bee, ſeeking reſt and quietneſſe, by faith in the Sonne of God, wee be inuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the ſnares of calamity and tribulation; for it is the good-will and pleaſure of our heauenly Father, to lay this yoke vpon vs whilſt we liue here vpon earth. Firſt, to call to our remembrance, the generall Apoſtaſie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection by vs in our firſt Parents, made from the Lord our God: for the world knoweth not the fearefull diſeaſe, lothſome contagion, and fierce wrath and indignation, thereby violently drawne vpon the whole poſterity: and conſequently, by the reares of repentance, and faith in the Mediator, ſue not for atonement, nor ſeeke to bee reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto this conſuming fire: Therefore, it pleaſeth the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8939:24"/>wiſdome of our great Aduocate, to lay this yoke vpon the neckes of his Diſciples, that by theſe ſowre fruits, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the bitterneſſe of the roote, they may thereby be incited and ſtirred vp to ſue vnto the true <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 2.19. &amp; 4.40.</note> IESVS CHRIST, for curing theſe poiſoned waters, and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this deadly meale: Secondly, thereby to beget in our hearts a deeper conſideration, and higher eſteeem and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of our atonement and reconciliation made by the death and al-ſufficient ſacrifice of Ieſus Chriſt: the better the patient vnderſtands the danger of his diſeaſe, the more thankfull is he vnto the Phyſicion for his cure: the more euidences &amp; vnfallible arguments that men haue of death, the more ioifully and gladly do they receiue their pardon: hee that's adiudged to bee burnt quicke, eſcapes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with the loſſe of a finger, by this ſmall taſte better knowes the greatneſſe of the Iudge his fauor, then if ſo be he had not at all felt any heate of the fire: Euen ſo the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance of temporal afflictions, the leaſt part of that which our ſinnes haue deſerued at the hands of the Lord, makes vs vnderſtand the great obligation, wherin we are bound vnto the Sonne of God, by whom we are redeemed from ſo great damnation, and more thankful vnto his holineſſe for ſo great a bleſſing; for if ſo be theſe excrements be ſo heauy, what ſhould the whole burthen haue bin? if we find ſuch and ſo great difficulty in bearing the ſmalleſt and leaſt part: what if the whole deſert of our tranſgreſſions had bin layd vpon vs? Thirdly, the yoke of calamitie and tribulation ſerues for preuenting of future ſlips, according to that of the Prophet <hi>Danid:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.67. &amp; 71.</note> Before I was afflicted, I went aſtray, but now haue I kept thy word: And againe, It is good for me that I haue bin afflicted, that I might learne thy ſtatutes: for as the bitterneſſe of ſowre and vnſauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie things makes the ſuckling forbeare and refraine the dug, wherunto he otherwiſe he naturally inclineth. Iuſt ſo the bitterneſſe of calamitie and tribulation, which for Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity lieth heauy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deareſt of Gods children, makes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8939:24"/>them forſake and renounce the pleaſures of ſinne, from whence otherwiſe they could not ſo eaſily be weaned and kept backe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And learne of me:</hi> There is no doctrine more harſh and vnſauoury vnto the naturall man, then that of the croſſe; therefore when as mention is made thereof, vſually it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the wiſedome of Gods holy Spirit to ſubioyne words of encouragement and comfort, as in that Propheſie of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels tribulation in the land of <hi>Aegypt: Know for a ſuretie, that thy ſeede ſhall be a ſtranger in a Land that is not theirs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhall ſerue them, and they ſhall afflict them foure hundred yeeres, and alſo that Nation whom they ſhall ſerue, I will iudge, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſhall they come out with great ſubſtance:</hi> and againe, <hi>Theſe things haue I ſpoken vnto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.33.</note> 
               <hi>that in me yee might haue peace, in the world ye ſhall haue tribulation: but be of good cheere, I haue ouercome the world;</hi> as here in the Text which now we haue in hand, Chriſt in the beginning of the Verſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpoken of a yoke, leſt thereupon men ſhould bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and diſ-heartned from comming vnto him, he is not content to promiſe vnto them in the agony, &amp; greateſt heate of affliction reſt vnto their ſoules, that though the outward man periſh, yet the inward man ſhall be renewed day by day; though the body be dead, becauſe of ſinne, yet the ſpirit ſhall liue, becauſe of righteouſneſſe; though the fleſh be deſtroyed, yet the ſpirit ſhall be ſaued in the day of the Lord Ieſus: but for their further incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he addes two forcible and effectuall arguments, for begetting in their hearts patience and conſtancy in bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this yoke: the firſt whereof is taken from his own example, which ought ſo much the more to preuaile with vs, as he is is more worthy &amp; in the fauor of God then we; learne therefore of mee, that the father in this life will not haue his children free from the yoke of calamity and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation; for if we be without chaſtiſement, whereof all are partakers, we are baſtards and not the ſonne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God: becauſe the Lord whom hee loueth, he chaſtiſeth and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8939:25"/>euery ſonne, whom he receiueth; and certainly, if we ponder and weigh things in an euen ballance, this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but preuent euery leaſt beginning of diſcontent, that we taſte of no other cuppe, then that whereof the Sonne of God hath liberally drunke before, there is no other meaſure giuen vs, then that which Ieſus Chriſt hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly receiued:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>Hereunto</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>were ye called, becauſe Chriſt alſo ſuffered, leauing for vs an example that wee ſhould follow his ſteppes:</hi> and againe, <hi>Whom he did fore-know, he alſo did predeſtinate to be conformed to the Image of his Son:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note> that as hee in all meekneſſe and lowlineſſe of minde, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelfe to the good will and pleaſure of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father; ſo by his example wee might learne to doe the ſame: according to that of the Apoſtle: <hi>Being found in faſhion as a man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>hee humbled himſelfe, and became o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient vnto the death, euen the death of the Croſſe:</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Though he were a Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>yet learned hee obedience by the things which he ſuffered; Reioice greatly, O Daughter of Sion, ſhout, O Daughter of Ieruſalem, behold, thy King commeth vnto thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 9.9.</note> 
               <hi>hee is iuſt and hauing ſaluation, lowly, and riding vpon an Aſſe, and vpon a Colt, the Foale of an Aſſe.</hi> For herein ſtands the difference between the Godly and the wicked, in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying about the badges of guilt, that the one doth it with vnſpeakable wreſtling, repining, grudging, murmuring, and fretting againſt the Lord: but the other with al meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and lowlineſſe of minde, ſubmit themſelues vnder the afflicting hand of Almighty God, and why? becauſe they vnderſtand their afflictions to proceed from a louing and gracious Father, who will doe nothing but for their good, howſoeuer for the preſent his proceedings be ſowre and vnſauoury vnto the naturall man: but the wicked ſeeing nothing, but the fierce countenance of an angrie Iudge, fret and fume againſt him as the enemy and deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of their being. If the Iudgement of God be denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſt <hi>Cain</hi> for his offence,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.13.</note> as an vntamed Heifer hee will kicke againſt his Maker: My puniſhment is greater
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8939:25"/>then I can beare;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.18.</note> but let <hi>Samuel</hi> deliuer vnto <hi>Eli</hi> neuer ſo harſh newes, the groſſeſt of his carriage ſhall be, it is the Lord, let him doe what ſeemeth him good: If <hi>Ahito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> be diſgraced, the Gallowes ſhall bewray the impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable diſcontent of his heart: but although King <hi>Dauid</hi> be openly reproued for his ſinne, humble confeſſion is the worſt entertainement that hee giues the Lords meſſage, learne therefore of mee, for I am meeke and lowly in heart, and yee ſhall finde reſt vnto your ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My yoke is eaſie:</hi> The ſecond argument which Chriſt vſeth to perſwade ſuch as come vnto him, with patience and conſtancie to take his yoke vpon them, is taken from the eaſineſſe, and facilitie of the taske: things light and eaſie to bee performed are at the command of a Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, with great patience and conſtancy cagerly to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand; eſpecially, being exceeding profitable, and making for the good of the Patient, but ſo it is, that my yoke is eaſie, and my burthen light.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe of the perpetuall aſſiſtance of my holy Spirit, whereby you are ſtrengthened in the inner-man, the better to beare the afflictions which outwardly you ſuffer in the bodie: according to that of the Apoſtle:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>God is faithfull, who will not ſuffer you to bee tempted aboue that you are able, but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that yee may be able to beare it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is eaſie, becauſe of the vnſpeakable felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and happineſſe, which after ſmall continuance it brings vnto the Patient: <hi>Our light affliction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>which is but for a moment, vvorketh for vs a farre more exceeding, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall weight of glorie:</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>I reckon that the ſufferings of this preſent time are not worthie to bee compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the glorie which ſhall bee reuealed in vs.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of himſelfe, ſayth,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>Who now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in my ſuffering for you, and fill vp that which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind of the afflictions of Chriſt in my fleſh for his bodies ſake, which is the Church.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Wee reioyce in tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8939:26"/>my brethren, count it all ioy when ye fall into diuers temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My yoke.</hi> Firſt, becauſe according to my good will and pleaſure, I impoſe and lay the ſame vpon the necks of my followers: for afflictions come not vnto the Saints by chance, or fortune, but from the Lord; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 1.21. &amp; 5.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord giueth, and the Lord ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> And againe, <hi>Happie is the man whom God correcteth: therefore despiſe not thou the chaſtening of the Almightie, for he maketh ſore and bindeth vp, he woundeth and his hands make whole:</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly it is his yoke, becauſe in his owne perſon hee hath deepely taſted the bottome and verie dregges of this Cuppe; according vnto that of the Prophet, <hi>He is despiſed and reiected of men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 53.3, 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>a man of ſorrowes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with griefe: ſurely he hath borne our griefes, and carried our ſorrowes, he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities, the chaſtiſement of our peace was vpon him.</hi> Thirdly, hee calls it his yoke, for diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and diſtinctions ſake betweene the afflictions of the godly, and puniſhments of the wicked: the one beareth the yoke of Gods fierce wrath and indignation, becauſe of their abhominable tranſgreſſions; but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the yoke of fatherly correction: the one yoke is impoſed and layd on, for the deſtruction and ouerthrow of the patient; but the other, for the chaſtiſement of ſonnes, that thereby they may learne, not to prouoke their heauenly Father vnto further diſpleaſure. Fourthly and laſtly, Chriſt calls it <hi>my yoke,</hi> in regard of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious aſſiſtance of his holy Spirit, whereby hee comforts, vpholds, and ſtrengthens the hearts of his children, for the more patient and conſtant bearing of the ſame: <hi>For we haue not an High Prieſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>which cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities, but was in all things tempted as wee are, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he might be a mercifull and faithfull High Prieſt in things pertaining to God, to make reconciliation for the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8939:26"/>ſinnes of the people. Bleſſed therefore be God, euen the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Father of mercies, and the God of all comfort, who comforteth vs in all our tribulation, that we may be able to comfort them which are in any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by the comfort wherewith we our ſelues are comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God.</hi> To whom, the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt, be all honour, prayſe, and glorie, now, and for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
